嘿，你们好
hey, what's up guys
我是Cherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
my name is Cherno, welcome back to my OpenGL series
所以今天我们会讨论索引缓冲区
so today we're gonna be talking all about index buffers
上一次我们也讨论了着色器
last time we talked about shaders and also
在那之前是顶点缓冲区
before that vertex buffers
如果你还没看过的话，去找到那些视频看看吧
check out those videos, if you haven't already
但今天我们会关注一个新东西
but today we're gonna be focusing on something new
它叫索引缓冲区
something called an index buffer
现在
now
在我定义什么是索引缓冲区之前
before I kind of define what an index buffer actually is
然后我们开始讨论
and we get into talking about
为什么我们需要用它们，以及它们到底是什么
why we want to use them, and what they actually are
让我们先考虑一个基础的问题
let's think of...let's just think of a basic problem
我们可能在图形编程中
that we might have in graphics programming
我们想去画一个正方形
we want to draw a square
直到现在，我们都只是画了一个三角形
up until now, we've just been drawing a triangle
那就是，它只是显示在屏幕上的一个独立的三角形
that's it just one single triangle on the screen
一切正常
everything's been fine
它看起来像是
it looks like
我们在我们代码中实现的那种方式非常高效
the way that we're kind of doing that in our code is pretty efficient
然后，让我们尝试画一个正方形吧
however, let's try and draw a square
所以我们实际上要做的就是去画一个正方形
so what do we need to do to actually draw a square well
我们显卡实际上做的一切东西
everything that our GPU actually does
都可以归结到三角形
comes down to triangles
我们稍后可能会讨论为什么会是那样
we might talk later about why that is
但对于现在, 只需要绘制一个三角形, 差不多
but for now, just picture a triangle, as pretty much
使用最少的顶点吧
the smallest number of vertices
我们需要展示一个平面
we need to represent one flat
有法线的平面
kind of plane with a normal that is
和一个曲面的法线, 指向一个方向
with a surface normal that is pointing in a single direction
因为显卡倾向于使用三角形作为
because of that GPU tend to kind of use triangles as
它们渲染一些原始的东西, 对吧
they're rendering kind of primitive, right
所以一切都基于三角形
so everything's based on triangles
所以当我们试着画两个正方形的时候或者
so when we try and draw two squares or rather
抱歉, 当我们画正方形的时候
sorry, when we try and draw a square
它真的只是一个三角形
it's really just a triangle
对吧, 或者两个三角形
right, or specifically two triangles
我们画的任何东西都是由三角形组成的
anything we draw is made up of triangles
所以正方形就是两个三角形, 对吧, 1  2
so a square is just two triangles, right, 1 2
那就是它, 两个三角形
that's it, two triangles
所以让我们试着用当前的设置来做, 并且
so let's try and do that with our current setup, and
看看会发生什么
see what happens
所以在这里
so over here
我们这里基本上有一组顶点
we have basically this set of vertices here for you
但是让我们
but let's just
让我们运行这个应用程序
let's just run this application
看看我们到底得到了什么
see what we've actually got
我们在这儿看到了这个三角形
we've got this triangle here
漂亮的蓝色三角形
nice blue triangle
如果我们看一下代码
if we take a look at the code
我们有这三个顶点, 如果我们画一个正方形
we've got these three vertices, if we try and draw a square
好吧, 让我们想一下
well, let's think about that for a minute
我在这儿直接打开illustrate(Adobe的一款工业标准矢量插画软件)
I'm just gonna open illustrate here
所以我可以给你们画个图解
so I can draw you a diagram
而不是我们像这样画我们的三角形
instead of us kind of drawing our triangle like this
就像现在这样
which is what it is right now
我们想画一个正方形
we want to kind of draw a square
在两个三角形外
out of two triangles
而我们可以实现那个的方式就是通过
and the way we can do that is just by
像那样画两个三角形
drawing two triangles like that
明白吧, 所以我们在这儿有了一个三角形
right, so we kind of have one triangle over here
以及在这儿的一个三角形
and one triangle over here
那么分别画出这两个三角形
and drawing those two triangles separately
有点像那样, 那么然后像这样
kind of like that, and then like that
或者你想怎么做都行
or however you want to do it
实际上, 我们可能会像这样去实现它
in fact, we're probably going to do it like this
并且然后像那样
and then like that
所以这就是我们实际上如何
so that's how we're going to actually
构成那个正方形
make up that square
所以我们来讨论一下这些可能是什么位置
so let's talk about which positions these might actually be
所以这里的这个
so this one over here
我们知道xy都会是-0.5
we know is kind of going to be -0.5 in both x and y
那就是我们在这里得到的, 对吧
that's kind of what we've got over here, right
我们来看下一个
the next one if we come over here
我们把它画成逆时针的形式
we kind of draw this in an anti clockwise fashion
然后我们先画出这个顶点
then we're going to be drawing this vertex first
然后是这个顶点, 然后是这个顶点, 对吧
then this vertex, then this vertex, right
所以当我们回到我们的源码
so if we go back to our source
那么那里的xy基本上都是-0.5
so that's basically going to be -0.5 in x and y
这个顶点的x就是0.5
this one's going to be positive 0.5
而然后y还是保持-0.5
and then still keeping negative 0.5 for y
那么然后我们将y提升到0.5
and then we're going to lift y up to positive 0.5
并且也像那样保持x
and also keep x like that
所以如果我们现在运行这个程序
so if we just run this program now
我们应该画出第一个三角形, 你可以看到那就是我们得到的
we should have that first triangle drawn, and you can see that's what we get
好的, 所以现在我们需要画第二个三角形
okay, so now we need to draw the second triangle
所以让我们在这儿先画出这个顶点
so let's start off with drawing this vertex here
然后这个顶点在这儿
then this vertex here
然后这个顶点继续逆时针运动
then this vertex here to kind of keep going in a counter clockwise fashion
所以回到我们的代码
so back to our code
而我们要在这里添加一些顶点
and we're going to add some vertices here
我要把这个6去掉
I'm just going to get rid of this six here
这样我们就能有我们需要的
so that we can have as many as we need
我将复制并粘贴这个顶点位置
I'm going to copy and paste this vertex position
因为它们是完全一样的
because it's going to be exactly the same
当然, 这两个顶点实际上是一样的
of course, these two vertices are actually the same
然后我再添加一个顶点, 也就是左上角
and then I'm going to add one more vertex for that'll be the top left corner
它的x是-0.5, y是0.5
which is going to be -0.5 x and positive 0.5 y
那么然后最后, 这个顶点也和这个顶点是一样的
and then finally, this vertex over here is also kind of the same as this vertex
所以那和第一个是一样的
so that'll be the same as the very very first one here
所以现在我们有六个顶点
so now we have six vertices
如果我下来到这儿
if I come down over here
我们需要调整顶点缓冲区的大小
we need to adjust the size of our vertex buffer
这样它实际上就可以接收所有的内存
so that it can actually take in all of this memory
所以我想做的而不是只把这个改成12
so I'm going to instead of just changing this to be 12
我想把它写成这样, 6*2*sizeof(float)
I want to make it six times two time sizeof float
因为, 当然, 在这儿的每个顶点
because, of course, each vertex here
都是两个浮点型大小, 并且我们有六个顶点
is a size of two floats, and we have sex vertices
这只是读起来容易一些
it's just a little bit easier to read
如果我滚动到这里
if I scroll down here
我需要改动的另一件事
the other thing I need to change
就是代替只绘制三个顶点
is instead of just drawing three
我们当然需要绘制六个顶点
we of course need to draw six
所以在我的glDrawArrays函数
so in my glDrawArrays
我会把它改成6
I'm going to change this to six
那么然后这里是5
and then here at five
好了, 很酷
all right, there we go pretty cool
所以现在我们有了一个正方形
so we've got an actual square now well
具体地说
specifically
这是一个长方形, 因为我们的窗口是
this is a little bit rectangular, because our window is
实际上不是正方形的
actually not not square
这看起来很好
so that seems pretty good
我的意思是我们已经画出了一个正方形
I mean we've managed to draw a square
它并不太难
it wasn't too difficult
但是有些东西
but there is something
有点不太理想
a little bit sub optimal
关于我们画这个正方形的方式
about the way that we're actually drawing this square
并且特别地, 让我们看一下我们的顶点
and specifically let's take a look at our vertices
所以回到这里, 在我们实际的顶点数组中
so back over here, in our actual vertex kind of array that we have here
你可以看到我们实际上在做的是
you can see that what we're actually doing is
我们在自我重复
we're repeating ourselves
我们在这里有两个顶点, 对吧
we've got this vertex over here twice, right
并且我们得到了这个
and we've got this one
第一个和最后一个也是完全一样的
this first and last one is also exactly the same
这些并不是完全唯一的
these aren't completely unique
也就是说我们现在做的是
which means what we're actually doing is
我们在复制我们的内存
we're kind of duplicating our memory
我们在显存中存储相同顶点位置的相同字节
we're storing these same bytes of the same vertex positions in our GPU memory
存储了多次, 而那个有点浪费
multiple times, and that's a little bit wasteful
因为显存并不是无限的, 而我们想要降低它的内存使用
because well GPU memory isn't just infinite, and we do want to keep that down
所以我们能做的就是使用一个叫做索引缓冲区的东西
so what we can actually do is use something called an index buffer
这允许我们重用现有的顶点
which allows us to reuse existing vertices
因为如果你仔细想想
because if you think about it
我们确实想说的
what we really want to say
就是像这样绘制这三个顶点
is draw kind of these three vertices like this
并且然后可能
and then maybe
绘制这三个顶点来组成第二个三角形, 这很简单
draw these three vertices to make up the second triangle, this is much easy
这样就简单多了
this is gonna be much easier
如果我就用图解来像你们展示这个
if I just show you on this on diagram
我不知道我为什么要这么做
I don't know why I'm doing this
所以让我们回到illustrator
so let's go back to illustrator
这将是美妙的
it'll be fantastic
如果我们只是说, 让我把这里的颜色可能换成红色
if we could just say, and let me just change my color over here to maybe red
如果我们只是说我想画出这个顶点
if we could just say I want to draw this vertex
然后我需要绘制这个顶点
then I want to draw this vertex
并且然后我也需要绘制这个顶点
and then I want to draw this vertex again
在这儿这个新顶点
this new vertex over here
并且然后再是第一个顶点, 对吧
and then this first vertex again, right
因为这就是我们画这部分所需要的
because that would be all we would need to really say to draw this part
然后像那样把那部分也画出来, 好了
and then just draw that part as well like that, okay
所以我们要避免自我重复
so we want to avoid kind of repeating ourselves
或者更确切地说, 就是多次使用相同的内存
or specifically just having the exact same memory multiple times
那真的很浪费内存
that's very wasteful
现在显然对于正方形, 或者矩形来说
now obviously for a square, or for a rectangle
它可能看起来并不浪费
it might not seem wasteful
因为它没有太多的东西
because there's not much to it
我的意思是, 是的, 我们的顶点缓冲区中有50%的数据
I mean, yes, we do have 50% more data in our vertex buffer
因为我们存储了两个额外的顶点而不是四个
because we're storing two extra vertices instead of storing four
实际上我们存储了六个顶点
we're storing six
然而, 当你想到3D模型时, 对吧
however, when you think about a 3D model, right
也许你的游戏中有一个角色, 一艘宇宙飞船, 或者其他什么, 对吧
maybe you've got a character in your game, or a spaceship, or whatever it may be, right
每一个组成那个飞船或那个角色的独立三角形
every single triangle that makes up that ship or that character
会被连接到另一个三角形, 对吧
is going to be connected to another triangle, right
这意味着你已经立马重复了至少两个顶点
which means that you're immediately already repeating at least two vertices
并且然后也许那儿上面还有一个三角形
and then maybe there's another triangle up there
对吧, 所以
right, so
你可以看到这是如何逐渐失控的
you can kind of see how this just kind of escalates out of control
并且你可能有很多遍历
and you might have so many traverses
并不只是那样
not only that
但是当你实际渲染
but when you're actually rendering
渲染丝线图形和潜在的类似
rendering thready graphics and potentially in like
也许你用的是基于物理的渲染
maybe you're using something like physically based rendering
你的顶点可能很大
your vertices might be pretty big
你可能有顶点位置
you might have vertex positions
由法线切线颜色组成的正常的纹理坐标
normally texture coordinates by normal tangents colors
它们可能都在一个顶点上
you might that might all be in one vertex
那么如果你不得不复制整个缓冲区
and if you have to duplicate that entire kind of buffer
它一次又一次地构成了那个实际的顶点
that makes up that actual vertex again and again and again
那是完全不现实的, 对吧
that's just going to be completely unrealistic, right
只用一个简单的索引会更快更有效
just having a simple index instead is going to be much quicker and much more efficient
所以让我们
so let's let's just
让我们来转换一下这种顶点缓冲
let's just convert this kind of vertex buffer that we have
现在让我们给它添加一个索引缓冲区, 并删除那些
now let's add an index buffer to it, and remove those
重复的冗余内存
kind of that duplicate redundant memory
所以当我回到我的源码
so if I go back to my source code over here
我要做的是创建一个索引缓冲区, 所以
what I'm going to do is make an index buffer, so
我们做这个的方法, 好吧
the way that we do this in kind of well
这儿有其他去思考它的方法, 真的
here's another way to think about it really
当我们去掉这个数组中所有多余的东西, 对吧
if we get rid of all of the redundant stuff inside this array, right
所以这里只有唯一的顶点位置
so that we only have unique vertex positions here
我将做的就是去掉这个
what I'll do is I'll get rid of this one
因为它是重复的
because it's the duplicate
并且我把最后一个去掉, 因为它也是重复的, 对吧
and I'll get rid of that last one, because it's the duplicate, right
所以现在我们的数组基本上就是这样
so now what we have is basically this
而当我回到illustrator, 这样的话
and if I go back to illustrator, just so
你们可以想象这多么简单
you guys can visualize this a little bit easier
当我让它变成绿色或类似颜色的时候
when I make this color green or something like that
对吧, 这是我们的索引0, 这是索引1
right, this this is our index zero, this is index one
这是索引2, 以及这个是索引3, 好了
this is index two, and this is index three, okay
所以0 1 2 3, 在这儿每行一个
so 0 1 2 3 each line over here
我把它分离成一行一行的
I've kind of divided it line by line
每行就是一个独立的顶点, 并且当然
is a single vertex, and of course
如果我们从0开始给这些顶点编号
if we kind of number these vertexes starting from zero
我们得到了一个索引的排序
we get a sort of index
所以当我创建
so if I was to create
一个无符号整型数组在这儿, 就叫indices, 并且
an unsigned int array here, called indices, and
我基本上只是想画出和之前一样的正方形, 我可以说的就是
I just wanted to basically draw that same square that I had before, what I could say is
使用第一个和第二个顶点
use the first vertex the second
以及第三个顶点, 就像那样得到第一个三角形
and the third vertex, to kind of get this first triangle over here like that
所以那会是0 1 2
so that will be zero one and two
如果我们像这样引用顶点, 如同它们的索引
if we kind of refer to our vertices like this, as if they were indexed which they are
我们得到了这个顺序, 对吧, 0 1 2
we kind of get this order, right, so 0 1 2
那么然后, 对于第二个三角形, 我需要2 3 0这样的顺序索引, 对吧
and then, for the second triangle, I want to do two three and zero, right
因为那是这个位置2, 对吧, 然后是3和0
because that's this position two, right,z three and zero
这就是我们如何画这个三角形, 第二个三角形的
which is how we can kind of draw this triangle, the second one
所以就是2 3 0, 并且那实际上就是一个索引缓冲区
so 2 3 and zero, and that is actually an index buffer
我们刚刚创建了准确的数据, 我们需要说明
we've just created exactly the data, we need to tell
OpenGL, 如何去渲染这个三角形或者是这个正方形
OpenGL, how to render this triangle or either this square
而不是使用而不是给它提供
without using, without providing it
冗余或重复的顶点位置, 所有这些所有的顶点
with redundant or duplicate vertex positions, and all of that all vertices
我刚才应该说, 因为很明显
I should just say, because obviously
在这个例子中, 我们只有位置
in this case, we've just got positions
但它们会是
but they could be
它们里面可能有更多的数据
they could be a lot more data in there
所以现在剩下的就是
so now all that remains is
实际上取代它的数据就是
actually instead of having this data here
这些在CPU上的indices
these indices here on the CPU
我们实际上需要把它们发送到显卡上
we want to actually send them to the GPU
并且然后, 告诉OpenGL用它们去渲染, 明白吧
and then, tell OpenGL to render using them, okay
而我们实现那个的方式
and the way that we do that is very
非常非常像我们实际上创建一个顶点缓冲区的方式
very similar to the way that we actually make a vertex buffer
所以让我们复制这个
so let's copy this
我要把这个放在顶点属性后面
I'm gonna put this after our kind of vertex attribute stuff
就把它粘贴在这儿吧
just paste it here
我把这个重命名为ibo
I'm gonna rename this ibo
代表了索引缓冲区对象
which stands for index buffer object
因为它有点儿像我们的id或者是我们的对象
because it's kind of like our id or our object
表示这个特定的索引缓冲区
which represents this particular index buffer
我们去生成一个缓冲区
we're going to generate a buffer
和我们生成普通缓冲区的方法一样, 这儿唯一真正的区别
the exact same way that we generate a normal buffer, the only real difference here
就是代替把它作为一个数组缓冲区绑定
is that instead of binding this as an array buffer
或者具体地说是那个插槽
or specifically to that slot
就是那个GL_ARRAY_BUFFER插槽
to that GL_ARRAY_BUFFER slot
我们会把它绑定到一个GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER
we're binding it to a GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER
好了, 那么当我们确定了我现在做的那些
okay, and once we'll just make sure that I'm doing that
就是绑定缓冲区和缓冲区数据
for both the bind buffer and buffer data
我们现在绑定的缓冲区就是, 当然
the buffer that we're binding is, of course
就是这个我们刚生成的ibo
this ibo that we've just generated
并且最后当我们提供给它数据
and finally when we supply it with data
而不是提供给它positions
instead of supplying it with positions
我们提供给它这些indices
we supply it with these indices
所以我就写indices
so I'll just write indices
那么然后, 当然, 它们的大小是
and then of course the size of them is
在这个例子中就是六个无符号整型
in this case going to be six unsigned ints
现在, 记住那个, 这里我选择使用无符号整型
now, keep in mind that, I've chosen to use unsigned ints here
因为将来我们可能会使用无符号整型
because we'll probably likely be using unsigned int in the future
但是, 你可以只使用无符号字符或无符号短整型
however, you can just use unsigned char or unsigned short
如果你想设置字符的内存
if you want to kind of set memory char
当然是一个字节, 短整型的是两个字节
of course being one byte, short being two bytes
整型是四个字节, 所以它们比一个字符需要更多的内存, 然后
integers are four bytes, so they are a lot more memory than say a char, however
显然, 你会受到限制, 如果你使用一个字符
obviously you have the restrictions of, if you use a char
你只有一个无符号字符
you only have an unsigned char
你只有0到255个数字
you only have zero to two fifty five
所以你只能有256个不同的indices
so you can only have 256 different different indices
我们将在所有这些例子中使用无符号整数
we're going to use unsigned ints for all these examples
因为在这种情况下不会有任何可衡量的性能差异
because there's not going to be any measurable performance difference in this case
并且在以后
and in the future
当我们有相当复杂的模型时, 我们可能希望使用无符号整型, 不管如何
when we have pretty complex models, we'll likely want to be using unsigned ints, anyway
这儿的关键就是它必须是无符号的
the key here is that it has to be unsigned
你不能使用一个符号类型, 明白吧
you cannot use a signed type, okay
后面还会有更多关于它必须是无符号的内容, 所以在这里
it has to be unsigned more on that later, so down here
所有这些验证了我们确实有6倍无符号整型大小
all this verify that we do have six times unsigned ints
这就是我们在实际数组中得到的
which is exactly what we've got in our actual array
那么然后我们当然把它放到这里
and then we're of course taking it in over here
看起来很不错, 对吧
so looks pretty good, right
那么我们还需要改变什么
so what else do we need to change
好吧, 我们最需要改变的最后一个东西便是我们真正的DrawCall
well, the last thing we need to change is our actual DrawCall
而不是glDrawArrays
instead of being glDrawArrays
它变成了glDrawElements
it becomes glDrawElements
并且这里的模式和我们画三角形是一样的
and the mode here is the same with we're drawing triangles
这个count就是6
the count is going to be six
因为我们要绘制六个索引
because we're drawing six indices
这是我们绘制索引的数量
this is the number of indices we're drawing
而不是我们绘制顶点的数量
not the number of vertices we're drawing
这个type就是在索引缓冲区中数据的类型
the type is the type of data that is in the index buffer
在这个例子中是GL_UNSIGNED_INT
which in this case is GL_UNSIGNED_INT
而最后这是指向那个索引缓冲区的一个指针
and finally this is a pointer to that index buffer
现在因为我们得到了一个绑定
now because we've got a bound
在这个插槽里
in this actual slot here
我们实际上, 你可以看到glBindBuffer(GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER)
we've actually you can see glBindBuffer GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER
这个GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER就是一个索引缓冲区的插槽
this GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER is a slot for index buffers
并且我们已经把我们的ibo绑定到那儿了
and we've bound our ibo to there
我们实际上不需要在这里放任何东西, 所以我可以写一个空指针
we don't actually have to put anything here, so I can just write an null pointer
就是这样
and that's it
这就是我们所得到的
that's all we've got
这是绘制我们三角形的实际DrawCall指令
this is the actual DrawCall that draws our triangle
使用六个这种顶点, 对吧
using six kind of vertices, right
但你明显可以看到我们的顶点缓冲
but you can see obviously our vertex buffer
实际上只有四个顶点, 然后我们把它编入索引
only actually has four vertices, and then we've indexed into that
所以我们按f5来运行这个程序
so let's hit f5 to run this program
然后你可以看到我们得到了一个漂亮的矩形
and you can see we get a beautiful rectangle
现在那真是太棒了
now that's great
我没有提到这些必须是无符号的一些原因
I didn't mention something about these having to be unsigned
这将会很好地引导到OpenGL系列的下一期
and this is actually going to lead it great into the next OpenGL episode
但让我们还是故意犯一些错误吧
but let's just deliberately make some kind of mistake
这很容易在不经意间做出来
that's pretty easy to accidentally make
让我们不写GL_UNSIGNED_INT, 因为某些原因
let's just say that instead of writing GL_UNSIGNED_INT, for some reason
我在这儿写GL_INT, 好了
here I wrote GL_INT, okay
看起来很无恶意, 我是说
looks pretty harmless, I mean
是的, 无符号整型在这儿真的有那么大的区别
yeah, unsigned int is there really that much of a difference
我的意思是, 很明显这里是
I mean obviously there is
但是假设我们不知道这个
but let's just say that we didn't know that
按f5, 看一下
let's hit f5 and look at that
我们看到了一个黑窗口
we get a black screen
我们没有看到任何东西在这个终端打印
we get absolutely nothing printing in the console
除了OpenGL版本
except for that OpenGL version
那个还在这儿
that what's going on here
你所做的是你用了无效的, 你用了整型
well what you've done is you've used an invalid, you've used int
然而这个缓冲区或任何索引缓冲区
whereas this buffer or any index buffer
必须由无符号整型组成
has to be made up of unsigned integers
不是符号整型
not signed integers
无符号整型
unsigned integers
所以, 在我们的例子我们当然知道问题是什么
so, of course in our case we know what the problem is
我们把这个还原回来
we could just bring this back
但你可以想象, 有些人是如何做的
but you can imagine, how some people
当他们写这段可能犯错的代码时
when they write this code might make the mistake
我以前做过, 可能有好几百次了
I've made it before, hundreds of times probably
而我想知道为什么我的屏幕是黑色的
and I've wondered why do I have a black screen
这将引导我们进入下一期
this is going to lead us into our next episode
那是关于OpenGL错误的
which is going to be about OpenGL errors
以及特别是我们能做什么来处理OpenGL中的错误
and specifically what we can do to deal with errors in OpenGL
因为你可以看到, 如果我给它一个无效的枚举(整型)
because you can see, if I just give it an invalid enum
就像我刚才做的那样, 对吧然后
like I just did, right, right then
它什么都不会告诉我们
it's not gonna say anything to us
我们不知道自己做错了什么
we have no idea what we've done wrong
相反, 我们得到了一个黑屏, 什么都不能用
instead we get a black screen and nothing's working
诊断调试绝对是一场噩梦
that can be an absolute nightmare to diagnose a debug
尤其是OpenGL新手
especially if you're new to OpenGL
所以下次我们会讲到错误, 以及
so next time we're going to talk about errors, and
我们对它们能做些什么呢
what we can do about them
我们如何才能最好地从OpenGL获得错误报告
how we can best kind of get error reporting back from OpenGL
并且就像, 基本上就是在OpenGL中充分利用错误
and like, basically just make the best of errors in OpenGL
这样我们就能立刻知道, 当一些东西错了的时候
so that we can know immediately, when something goes wrong
并且特别是哪里出了问题
and specifically what goes wrong
那将会造成很多糟糕的情况
that's going to be making a lot of a bad situation
因为OpenGL告诉你, OpenGL调试非常非常糟糕
because OpenGL just telling you right now, OpenGL debugging is very very bad
不管怎样, 我们来重述一下索引缓冲区
anyway, just to recap index buffers
我们实际上做的是
what we've actually done is
我们已经删除了我们这里的任何重复顶点
we've removed any kind of duplicate vertices that we may have here
我们在这个顶点缓冲区中得到了完全唯一的顶点
we've just got absolutely completely unique vertices in this vertex buffer
现在我们所做的就是在顶点缓冲区中创建了一个索引
now what we've done is we've created an index into that vertex buffer
这样我们就可以多次绘制顶点
to allow us to kind of draw vertices more than once
然后我们用这段代码把索引缓冲区发送给显卡
and then we've actually sent that index buffer to the GPU using this code here
用我们创建的东西
with what we've created one
然后我们把这些数据发送给显卡
and then we've actually sent this data to the GPU
使用这行代码
using this line here
并且然后最终
and then finally
我们使用glDrawElements绘制使用实际的元素缓冲区或索引缓冲区
we're using glDrawElements to draw using an actual element buffer or an index buffer
因为它们更常被称为(索引缓冲区)
as they're more commonly called
而不是glDrawArrays
instead of glDrawArrays
这个是顺序绘制顶点的
which is just going to kind of draw vertices sequentially
就这样
and that's it
这就是我们如何在OpenGL中使用索引缓冲区绘制正方形
that's how we can draw a square in OpenGL using an index buffer
并且这基本上就是你在这里看到的
and that basically what you see there
这个设置, 顶点缓冲区, 索引缓冲区, 以及glDrawElements的调用
this setup, vertex buffer, index buffer, and glDrawElements call
那可能就是在我们屏幕和OpenGL东西中看到的90%吧
that is probably how we read a 90% of our stuff onto our screen and OpenGL
即使是在全面的职业游戏中, 如triple-a游戏
even in a full-on professional, like triple-a game
那就是你实现它要做的
that's how you do it
glDrawElements是使用最多的函数
glDrawElements is the function to be using most of the time
不管怎样, 我希望你们喜欢这个视频
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果你喜欢的话, 你可以点击那个喜欢按钮
if you did, you can hit that like button
如果你想帮助支持这个系列
if you want to help support this series
而且要确保新视频尽可能多地完成制作
and make sure the new episodes come out as often as possible
同时还能得到一堆很酷的奖励
as well as get a bunch of really cool rewards
前往pateron.com/TheCherno
head on over to pateron.com/TheCherno
像往常一样, 向所有精彩的支持者大声喊出来
massive shout out as always to all of the wonderful supporters
是让这个视频成为可能
which make this video possible
没有他们什么都不是, 所以再次
would be nothing without them, so again
感谢你们, 你们可以继续讨论
thank you, you can keep talking about
我在本期视频中提到的内容, 通过登录TheCherno.com/discord
what I've just mentioned in this video, by going to TheCherno.com/discord
或者在下方留言
or just leave a comment below
你们用索引缓冲区吗, 因为你们应该没问题, 我是说
do you guys use index buffers, because you should be okay, I mean
我喜欢参与社区, 在这些视频的最后, 我想说
I like to kind of engage the community, so to speak at the end of these videos, and be like
嘿, 你们在干嘛
hey, what do you guys do
但在这种情况下, 显然你喜欢
but in this case obviously you like
我的意思是, 你应该对几乎所有的东西都使用索引缓冲区
I mean, you should be using index buffers with pretty much everything
很难想象有什么东西不应该使用索引缓冲区
hard to think of anything that shouldn't be using an index buffer
说实话
to be honest
所以这是一个真正的问题
so this is an even really a question
如果你需要使用索引缓冲区
if you need to be using index buffers
它们的存在是有原因的
they're there for a reason
并且它们是极好的
and they're wonderful
不管怎样, 希望你们喜欢这个视频
anyway, hope you guys enjoyed the video
下一期我们会
next time we're going to
深入研究OpenGL错误, 以及看看我们如何正确处理它们
dive into OpenGL errors, and see how we can handle them properly
并且我觉得这一期应该比较多争议
and that's that should be quite a fight episode I think
因为我看到的第一件事
because the No.1 thing I see
对于OpenGL新手, 我看到的第一件事
the No.1 thing I see with people who are new to OpenGL
他们总是在抱怨, 因为有些东西对他们不起作用
and they're always complaining, because something isn't working for them
那是因为
it's because
他们没有正确处理自己的错误
they're not dealing with their errors correctly
而他们得到的是黑屏
and what they get is the black screen
并且一切都是最糟糕的
and everything's the worst
而他们不知道发生了什么, 这很公平
and they have no idea what's going on and fair enough
OpenGL根本不能很好地处理这个
OpenGL doesn't handle this well at all
但是你们要为自己设置一些基本的调试工具
but setting up some basic debugging tools for yourself
并且一些调试代码也能很好地确保这一点
and some debug code as well can really go a long way into making sure that
你们会立马发现它
you will alert it immediately
当一些东西出错时候, 所以下次再见
when something is wrong, so I'll see you guys next time
拜
goodbye